emmi@emmi.dev | denver, co | emmi.dev | linkedin.com/in/emiliarusso

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My interests revolve around the cognition of preschool-aged children and their interactions with machines, specifically in the context of play. I am interested in learning and cognitive development via play and how it intersects with technology, particularly video games and mobile applications. As a professional software engineer, I strongly desire to use my skills to build impactful technology in a research-informed manner.

EDUCATION

The University of Chicago, Chicago, IL

June 2018

Bachelor of Science - Computer Science Bachelor of Arts with Honors - Psychology

GPA: 3.5

Psychology GPA: 3.7

Relevant coursework: Psychological Statistics, Psychological Research Methods, Intro to Developmental Psychology, Infancy, Child Development in the Classroom, Intro to Language Development, Conceptual Development, Language for Thought and Action, Cognitive Psychology, Social Psychology, Sensation and Perception, Usable Security and Privacy, Computers for Learning, Computational Linguistics

Awards: degrees conferred with general honors, Dean's List 2015, 2016, 2018

Honors Thesis: Parents' Response Times Provide Implicit Negative Evidence for Grammar Learning

Readers: Daniel Yurovsky (advisor, primary investigator), Susan Goldin-Meadow

Poster presentations:

Chicago Area Undergraduate Research Symposium, 2018 Midwest Cognitive Science Conference 2018 - *Outstanding Poster Award*

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Communication and Learning Lab (CaLLab), The University of Chicago

Primary Investigator: Daniel Yurovsky *Undergraduate Honors Thesis Researcher*

December 2016 - June 2018

- + Authored Parents' Response Times Provide Implicit Negative Evidence for Grammar Learning which was approved by Daniel Yurovsky and Susan Goldin-Meadow to earn an honors distinction in the Psychology department
- + Performed computational analyses on 3 large natural language corpora using Python and R to demonstrate the existence of a novel form of negative evidence that children may use to learn English grammar
- + Designed and implemented an online self-paced reading experiment that demonstrated a processing delay when adult readers are presented with over-regularized child utterances
- + Participated in lab meetings, discussing research and providing feedback to fellow lab members

Infant Learning and Development Laboratory, The University of Chicago

Primary Investigator: Amanda Woodward

Undergraduate Research Assistant

October 2015 - October 2016

+ Coded qualitative behavioral and EEG data to support Courtney Filippi's research on infant hand shaping and sensorimotor cortex activity

- + Participated in lab meetings, discussing relevant research and lab members' work
- + Recruited, scheduled, and escorted families to participate in research

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Brandfolder by Smartsheet, Denver, CO

Senior Software Engineer I Full Stack Software Developer (Software Engineer II)

April 2021 - Present November 2019 - April 2021

- + Awarded Smartsheet's 2023 Q1 Brightspot award for the 'Earn trust' core competency
- + Organized work, reviewed and contributed code to lead teams of 2-7 software engineers to build and update many features core to Brandfolder's offerings.
- + Collaborated closely with Product and Customer Experience team members to resolve customer issues weekly
- + Mentored junior developers and supported coworkers in areas of passions like TypeScript, testing, and accessibility best practices

Microsoft, Redmond, WA

Software Engineer I

August 2018 - November 2019

- + Developed reporting features across Microsoft's Azure DevOps product by writing and reviewing code as a member of one of its only horizontal teams
- + Served as feature lead for displaying work rollup progress on Azure DevOps backlogs
- + Monitored live site health, managed and tuned automated alerts, facilitated daily stand-up, and worked to resolve bugs and customer issues during on-call engineer rotations

Square, San Francisco, CA

Software Engineer Intern - Developer Platform

June - September 2017

Google

Engineering Practicum Intern - Cloud Marketplace Engineering Practicum Intern - Knowledge Panel Ul June - September 2016

June - September 2015

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Current stack: TypeScript/JavaScript, React, HTML + SCSS, Ruby on Rails, PostgreSQL, Git, Google Cloud

Exposure to: Docker, jQuery, AngularJS, C, Python, Java, R, SML